Preliminary Inventory of the Kenneth Crowe Papers. WAG.088
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Kenneth Crowe Papers
1981-1998
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Crowe, Kenneth C.
WAG.088
23 Linear Feet (23 boxes)
Historical/Biographical Note
Kenneth C. Crowe, was a journalist, writing for Newsday from 1963 until his retirement in 1999. In his early years at Newsday he specialized in foreign investment, and traveled widely in Europe and the Middle East. He was part of an investigative team that won the Pulitzer Prize Gold Medal in 1970 and went on to win a long list of professional awards and honors. From 1976 he was assigned to cover organized labor, and his columns on the subject became essential reading on the recent history of the New York-area labor movement. Crowe's research on Ron Carey's successful campaign for the presidency of the Teamsters resulted in the publication, in 1993, of his book, Collision: How the Rank and File Took Back the Teamsters.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists largely of files of research materials compiled during the writing of Kenneth Crowe's book, Collision: How the Rank and File Took Back the Teamsters (New York, Scribners, 1993). The material includes clippings, reports, court documents, agreements, audiotaped interviews, videotapes and notes, as well as editorial correspondence, drafts and reviews of the book.
Arrangement
The collection is unprocessed.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Kenneth Crowe in 2002 and 2003. The accession number associated with this gift is 2002.030.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Labor unions -- Elections -- New York (State) -- New York.; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York.; International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Stablemen, and Helpers of America; International Brotherhood of Teamsters. Local 804; Crowe, Kenneth C.
- 1996 Teamsters elections; legal cases; Local 807; Local 810; Giampa trial documents, articles; Independent Review Board reports; articles on racketerism in the IBT; Crowe research materials for articles/book on Teamsters., 1990s (Box 1)
- Materials on Ronald Carey versus R.V. Durham in 1991 IBT elections, including Crowe articles for Newsday;challenges and complaints about election process; charges and other court documents in U.S. versus IBT, et al.; Teamsters Local 507; Bakery Workers Local 19; racketering onviction of Harold Friedman; Jackie Presser death; Crowe book drafts of prologue through section six for Charles Scribners Sons and MacMillion(publisher)., 1987-1993 (Box 2)
- Trial transcripts, depositions, court petitions, ect. for 1988 United States v. International Brotherhood of Teamsters, et al.; 1986 IBT Constitution; 1989 union roster, 1986-1992 (Box 3)
- Notebooks: Interviews with Ron Carey, Judge Lacey, Ken Paff and others, expenses, recordkeeping, meeting notes; Porceedings: 24th convention IBT CWHA(1991); assorted hearings and studies; interview transcripts; trial opinion and order; frederick Lacey, Independ Administrator; Report VI of the Independent Administrator under the Consent Order, Article F.12, "Report to the Court;" Exhibits A-O Independent Administrator's Quarterly Report IV; Court document: Joint Appendix Volume III of IV., 1976-1992 (Box 4)
- Hoffa and Carey; Transcripts; Press Materials; Elections material, including accusations between camps of impropreties., 1990-1998 (Box 5)
- Frederick Lacey reports, letters, biography; Lacey "Report to the Court," including IBT financial reform, salaries, inspector general; IBT book interviews w/Jack Cox, Mike Riley, ect.; court documents/charges, including Locals 707, 239, 205, 231, 291, 682, 986, 493, 377; Articles, correspondence, legal documents regarding the murder of teamster Bruno Bauer; Ed ferguson; IBT VP Candidates; Teamsters book/Mastro and Genoese interviews, 1980-1991 (Box 6)
- Teamster Finanacial Crisis, 1993-1994; Carey Misc.; court depositions, motions, exhibits, decisions, settlements, ligigations, ect.; IBT Local 282; Teamsters RICO; Hoffex FBI Memo; IBT Local 560; Duke Law Journal on RICO; John Cronin's 1993 independent reviewer reports re Local 299; Jackie Presser court case; Judge Edelstein's 1990 decision, 1988-1994 (Box 7)
- Michael Moroney, special agent in charge of Department of Justice's attempt to sever La Cosa Nostra control in IBT; 1992 case against Barry Feinstein, Local 237 president; interviews with union officials; newspaper clippings of IBT history; Locals 237, 282, 813, 72, 858, 851; IBT General Secretary-Treasurer report; Local 295 story, 1977-1993; 1987-1993 (Box 8)
- 1981 IBT Convention proceedings; Central States Pension Fund; 1996 IBT Election; "Collision: How the Rank and File took back the Teamsters" reviews, correspondence, press materials; 1992 Convention and newspaper articles; Local 239; 1991 Convention; Giuliani, as U.S. attorney; Local 138; Local 295, 1981-1991 (Box 9)
- Carey campaign for 1991 IBT presidency general elections: mailers, campaign day articles; articles and materials related to the apparent rebirth of teamsters and loosing of mob control within the union; court documents: transcripts, exhibits, submissions, ect.; 1986 report to the President and the Attorney General: "The Edge: Organized Crime, Business and Labor Unions.", 1986-1994 (Box 10)
- IBT Lacey; Lacey "Report to the Court"; T-Book/Interviews; court documents/charges; Takeover Charges; Teamsters 282/FORE IV; Bauer Ferguson, Ed; IBT VP Candidates; T-Book/Mastro Interview; Genoese. (Box 11)
- Hoffa October 1996; IBT/Consent Decrees; Teamsters Elections; Teamsters Joint Council; IBT Election September 1998; Carey; Hoekstra Hearing October 14-15, 1997; Teamsters for a Democreatic Union; 1991Convention/Press Releases; Hoffa/Roach; Metz September 1998; Carey 1997; Teamsters 1998/Ken Hall; Teamsters 295 watch(Puccio)., 1990-1998 (Box 12)
- T-Book proposals; manuscript for 'Collision;' T-Book contract; T-Book sections; Carey Materials: film, notes, clippings, articles; Teamster Ron Carey Smear Story; WTF Names: clippings, articles, correspondence, notes; McCarthy materials; Jackei Presser's death notifications; Shea v. McCarthy(President) lawsuit; Mathis., 1988-1992 (Box 13)
- Oversight of Labor Depts. Investigation of Teamsters Central States Pension Fund Hearings; publications; Book proposal; Carey notes; 'Teamsters' maazines; Roy Lee WIlliams material; press photographs; IRB Carey trial proceedings; Carey/Hoffa clippings, Nov. 1997; Economic Data from Teamsters study., 1989-1998 (Box 14)
- Diana Kilmury; IBT Convention 1991; Teamsters internships 1996; Local 138, 707; Teamsters dues story; 'The New Teamsters' reports, press releases and packets; Teamsters strike impact story; articles; 'Teamsters Pensions: A PROD Analysis of Where the Money Goes' (1978); Teamsters takeover., 1978-1996 (Box 15)
- "Cleaning Up the Teamsters Union: A Three Year Progress Report" (1995); Crowe article; research material; Hoekstra/Teamseters; Caery/IRB trial; Carey appeal and Conboy's response; LEedham/September 1998; Local 594; RICO articles, background; T-Book/new section 5, section 3; Teamsters convention story (1995-1996); Master Freight 1998; 1993 National Master Freight Agreement; Hogan., 1995-1998 (Box 16)
- 1986 IBT Convention proceedings; The Edge: Organized Crime, Business, and Labor Unions; Hearings: Labor racketeering Activities of Jack McCarthy and the National Consultants Associated, Ltd.(1966), Organized Crime: 25 Years after Valachi (1988), Teamsters' Union Central States Pension Fund (1976); Initial Credentials report, 1996; FBI files: U.S. vs. IBT, et al., La Cosa Nostra, et al., 1966-1996 (Box 17)
- Teamsters book sections 11, 8; 1996 Ron Carey campaign materials; Articles, reports and research regarding mob structure, and organized crime's involvement in the IBT; 1997 IBT Election materials: Hoffa v. Carey; allegations of a smear campaign directed against Carey and other union officers., 1970s-1998 (Box 18)
- 1988, 1989 court documents: charges depositions, transcripts of proceedings, applications to the court; Reports to the IBT from the independent administrator, 1989-1990; 1991 Eastern Conference vote tally for IBT elections; Local 63; Delagates information for 1991 Convention; Carey materials; lists of locals; newspaper clippings., 1988-1992 (Box 19)
- The Edge: appdendix; court motions, transcripts, ect.; Local 285 IBT; Local 282 guards strike; Local 707; FORE; IBT campaign; Palladino; IBT Presidential campaign pre-convention., 1990-1996 (Box 20)
- Publications: 'Union Democracy Reviews,' 1986-1993; 'Labor Notes,' 1983-1997, 'PROD,' 1976-1977; 'PROD Dispatch;' 'Convoy Dispatch,' 1984-1998, 'The Working Teamster.', 1976-1998 (Box 21)
- Master Freight; Carey clippings; 1981 IBT Convention proceedings; Central States pension fund; 1996 IBT Election; Teamsters Central States bound clippings; 'Collision' reviews; correspondence, press materials, book party materials; 1992 convention and articles; Local 239; William Brock; K-JUAn clippings and notes; 1991 Convention, 1989-1998 (Box 22)
- Audiotapes: Assorted interviews; Videotapes: 'Carey Inuaguration'; 'Jackie Presser: Teamster Boss'; Interview with Jimmy Hoffa; Hoffa, Mi6 and JFK. (Box 23)